<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A most true relation of the affaires of Cleve and Gulick as also of all what hath passed this last summer, since the most excellent and victorious prince, Maurice of Nassau, tooke the field with his armie, encamping before Rees in Cleueland: and the losse of Wesel, taken in by the Marques Spinola: vnto the breaking vp of our armie in the beginning of December last past. 1614. With the articles of the peace, propounded at Santen By Henrie Peacham.</title>
            <author>Peacham, Henry, 1576?-1643?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B15207</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855812</idno>
  <idno type="VID">177491</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240879928</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 19512</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S120617</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99855812e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B15207)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177491)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1000:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A most true relation of the affaires of Cleve and Gulick as also of all what hath passed this last summer, since the most excellent and victorious prince, Maurice of Nassau, tooke the field with his armie, encamping before Rees in Cleueland: and the losse of Wesel, taken in by the Marques Spinola: vnto the breaking vp of our armie in the beginning of December last past. 1614. With the articles of the peace, propounded at Santen By Henrie Peacham.</title>
                  <author>Peacham, Henry, 1576?-1643?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[42] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Stansby for Iohn Helme, and are to be sold at his shop in Saint Dunstans Church-yard, vnder the Diall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴ F²  (-A1).</note>
                  <note>Claims to correct the account in STC 14838: Newes from Gulick and Cleve.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Newes from Gulick and Cleve.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Jülich (Duchy) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Cleve (Duchy) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177491:1"/>
            <p>A MOST TRVE RELATION OF <hi>THE AFFAIRES</hi> OF CLEVE AND <hi>GVLICK,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>As also</hi> Of all what hath passed this last sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, since the most Excellent and Victorious Prince, MAVRICE <hi>of</hi> NASSAV, <hi>tooke the field with his</hi> Armie, encamping before <hi>Rees</hi> in <hi>Cleueland:</hi> and <hi>the losse of</hi> Wesel, <hi>taken in by the Marques</hi> SPINOLA:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vnto the breaking vp of our Armie</hi> in the beginning of December last past. 1614.</p>
            <p>With the Articles of the <hi>Peace, propounded at</hi> SANTEN.</p>
            <p>By Henrie Peacham.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Creditis avectos hostes?</hi>—</l>
               <l>—<hi>Sic notus Vlysses?</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>W. Stansby</hi> for <hi>Iohn Helme,</hi> and are to be sold at his shop in Saint <hi>Dunstans</hi> Church-yard, vnder the Diall. 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:177491:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Stirps</hi> GVLIELMIADVM <hi>generosa, Scientia</hi> COCI,</l>
                  <l>WELBEI <hi>probitas,</hi> OGLAEI <hi>bellica virtus:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Antea diuersis dede rant quae singula nomen,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cuncta modo in meritos coëuntunius honores.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Henritus Peacham.</hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177491:2"/>
            <head>TO THE TRVLY HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE, SIR IOHN OGLE KNIGHT, COLONELL OF A REGIMENT OF FOOTE, VNDER <hi>the Lords the Estates of the vnited</hi> Provinces: And Lord Gouernour <hi>of the Forces in the Towne of</hi> VTRECHT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O giue testimonie of my thankefulnesse vnto you, for many fauours, and your honorable respect of me, I present you with this, the fruit of my leisure, for the which also I am beholden vnto you since my returne from the Armie before <hi>Rees;</hi> not that, as some may imagine, I meant to carrie Pearles into <hi>Persia,</hi> or Owles to <hi>Athens,</hi> bring you newes of that you know alreadie, better then my selfe, being interessed in this, as in all other the most important actions that concerne the Field in these vnited Provinces, hauing had your Regiment in the Armie, and these things done in a manner before your dore; but that, whatsoeuer I haue seene with mine owne eyes, or receiued by sound Relation of others, might vnder your name winne a better reputation with the
<pb facs="tcp:177491:3"/>World, to whom I doe assure me, for your sake such as it is it will be welcome. The occasion of it was the satisfaction of many honorable and my worthy friends in <hi>England,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired mee at my comming ouer (as it is commonly the parting request of friends) to write such newes as hapned, yea though a priuate iournall of things of small moment seene or done vpon the way, which haue also their delight aswell as the most serious affaires. For their sakes haue I done it, as also for mine owne priuate recreation in the Armie, who haue beene euer a profest Enemie vnto <hi>Idlenesse;</hi> I take my leaue, from <hi>BREDA</hi> in <hi>Brabant.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordships truly. HENRIE PEACHAM.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:177491:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here being come vnto my hands this last Summer (at my being in the Low Countries) a ridiculous and lying Pamphlet, touching this present subiect; for the loue I euer bare to sacred truth, and the satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of many good spirits, who though they rest at home, as vpon their Center, yet haue their motions in the remotest parts: I haue publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed this little, but true, discourse of such actions and occurrences as haue been worthie the obseruance since either Armie aduanced to the field in the Countries of <hi>Cleue</hi> &amp; <hi>Gulick,</hi> (whereof my selfe haue for the most part bin an eie-witnesse) being loth to take vpon credit more then I might well answere, knowing well enough the danger in medling ouer-far in affaires of State, and busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of Princes, which only regard hath caused me to touch some things more tenderly then perhaps I would, desiring herein rather to resemble the corke, by swimming lightly aboue, then the hooke, by diuing too deep to fasten my selfe where I could not easily get wel off. So that onely I haue contented mee with the bare narration of what is past, euen to the last day of the
<pb facs="tcp:177491:4"/>treatie at <hi>Santen.</hi> What is like hereafter to ensue, Time will determine, which I had rather he should doe then I, because I verily beleeue the blame will fall vpon him. Farewell good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whosoeuer.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Henry Peacham:</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="history">
            <pb facs="tcp:177491:4"/>
            <head>A MOST TRVE RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation <hi>of the affaires of</hi> CLEVE and <hi>GVLICK.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat I may not with any tedious imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinence of searching the causes of these motions from the reuolution of the heauens, and conditions of all things here below subiect to mutabilitie, adde (as it is sometimes affected) an ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious frontispice to a poore house and as Mountebanks wrap vp meane trifles in many papers; I willingly omit Preface, which as a slow Porter, oft times keepes vs without till wee haue lost our stomackes: and come to our intended Discourse, raising vp (as it were by the rootes) the first ground of difference concerning the now questioned Title of <hi>Cleue</hi> and <hi>Gulick.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Pedegree of the Dukes of</hi> CLEVE <hi>and</hi> GVLICK.</head>
               <p>ABout an hundred yeares since (conditionally the lands of <hi>Cleue, Gulick, Marck, Bergh,</hi> &amp;c. should for euer remaine vnited) there was a mariage solemnized
<pb facs="tcp:177491:5"/>betweene <hi>Iohn</hi> the sonne of <hi>Iohn</hi> Duke of <hi>Cleue,</hi> Earle of <hi>Marck,</hi> and Lord of <hi>Rauenstein,</hi> and <hi>Marie</hi> the daughter and heire of <hi>William</hi> Duke of <hi>Gulick,</hi> of <hi>Bergen,</hi> and of <hi>Rauensberge,</hi> who had issue, one sonne, and three daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>viz. Hans Willem, Sybilla,</hi> (who maried <hi>Iohn Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> vpon condition also, that if the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Marie</hi> should die without issue male, all the lands should descend vpon this <hi>Sybilla,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick</hi> her husband, and their heires, shee giuing a peece of money to her other sisters) <hi>Anna</hi> and <hi>Aemilia,</hi> who died issuelesse. Now <hi>Hans Willem</hi> succeeding, <hi>Anno</hi> 1546. maried <hi>Marie</hi> of <hi>Austria,</hi> the daughter of King <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> after Emperour, and obtained from <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, that if hee should decease without heires males by this <hi>Marie</hi> his wife, that the lands should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scend to the daughters begotten by him of the said <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie;</hi> which decree was also confirmed by the ensuing Emperours, <hi>Ferdinand, Maximilian,</hi> and the late <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulph.</hi> He had issue by <hi>Marie;</hi> First, <hi>Charles Frederick,</hi> who died in <hi>Italie</hi> vnmaried: Secondly, <hi>Hans Willem,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Munster,</hi> who succeeded, but died also with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out issue: Thirdly, <hi>Marie Helionora:</hi> Fourthly, <hi>Anna M gdalena:</hi> Fifthly, <hi>Magdalena:</hi> Sixthly, <hi>Sybilla. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Helionora,</hi> (the third childe) who maried <hi>Albert Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick</hi> Duke of <hi>Prussia,</hi> with assurance also vpon the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, that if <hi>Hans Willem</hi> and his wife died without issue male, that then these lands should descend vpon this his eldest daughter, maried to the Duke of <hi>Prussia,</hi> and her heires, he giuing to the other sisters a peece of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, but that to bee leuied of his owne goods, and not of the lands of <hi>Gulick</hi> or <hi>Cleue.</hi> And all this was onely to
<pb facs="tcp:177491:5"/>vnite these lands more strongly together. This <hi>Marie</hi> died a yeare before her brother, leauing issue by the Duke her husband foure children: <hi>viz. Anna,</hi> maried to <hi>Iohn Sigismond,</hi> Duke of <hi>Brandenburge,</hi> the chiefe Competitor, one other daughter maried to the olde
<note n="*" place="margin">That is, <hi>Elector.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Cueruorst,</hi> a third to the Duke of <hi>Curland,</hi> a fourth to the Lord <hi>Hans Zorgien,</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> brother to the <hi>Cuervorst,</hi> (or <hi>Elector.</hi>) The 4. and second daughter, <hi>Anna Magdalena, Anno</hi> 1574. maried to <hi>Philip Lodouick</hi> Duke of <hi>Newburgh,</hi> by whom shee had issue foure sons, besides daughters: <hi>viz. Wolfgang Willem,</hi> eldest, and one of the Competitors, <hi>Otho Henrick, Iohn Frederick,</hi> and <hi>Augustus. Magdalena,</hi> the 5. and third daughter, <hi>Anno</hi> 1579. maried with the Palsgraue, <hi>Iohn</hi> Duke of <hi>Zuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Newburghs</hi> brother, by whom shee had issue, three sonnes, and some daughters. <hi>Sybilla</hi> of <hi>Cleue,</hi> the 6. and fourth daughter, <hi>Anno</hi> 1610 maried <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Austria,</hi> Marckgraue of <hi>Burgou,</hi> the sonne of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Austria,</hi> and is yet without issue. Of these two youngest there is not any question. Now it may be coniectured, since <hi>Marie Helionora</hi> died a yeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her brother <hi>Hans Willem</hi> the late Duke, <hi>Wolfgang Willem</hi> (that is the Duke of <hi>Newburge</hi>) sonne to the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond sister <hi>Anna Magdalena,</hi> claimes these lands in his mothers right, as next of bloud to the late Duke at his death, and his sister; whereas <hi>Anna</hi> wife to the Duke of <hi>Brandenburge</hi> was but his Neece. And the said <hi>Anna</hi> claimes them as more vpon her by descent, as also by what particular interest was estated vpon her by her Grandfather <hi>Hans Willem</hi> in his life time. And me thinks <hi>Anna</hi> should succeed: for so did our <hi>Richard</hi> the second
<pb facs="tcp:177491:6"/>before his vncles, notwithstanding his father, the blacke Prince, died before his grandfather. But this succession <hi>per Saltum,</hi> hath sometimes weightie reasons in some Countries, where remaineth any freedome of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects election (beside the right of descent) where they finde it may profit or preiudice the common good.</p>
               <p>Now the Duke of <hi>Cleue</hi> being dead, and <hi>Leopoldus</hi> in possession of the Towne and Castle of <hi>Gulick,</hi> or <hi>Iuliers,</hi> for his Master the Emperour; the Kings of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, France,</hi> and the Estates of these vnited Prouinces, thought it not fitting that hee should nest himselfe there, to the preiudice of the lawfull heires or competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. Wherefore his Maiestie of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> with the Estates, sent a puissant Armie vnder the conduct of that braue <hi>Scipio</hi> of our age, the victorious Prince <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice</hi> of <hi>Nassau,</hi> who after no long, but a forcible siege, tooke both the Towne and Castle, in the yeare 1610. Which done, it was consented vnto and agreed, that a companie of either Competitor Prince should remaine in the Towne, now become neutrall, till the right were adiudged, vnder the command of <hi>Pithan,</hi> a <hi>Germaine,</hi> as Captaine of both, hauing command of the Castle. But <hi>Neuburg,</hi> whether hauing the States in iealousie, or relying vpon the strength of his owne Title, or through a vindictiue resolution, (which seemeth to be the truth indeed) after <hi>Pithan</hi> had complained of some secret practise of his, contrary to the former agreement, (as it is reported) began new plots, and by many secret meanes endeuoured to be himselfe wholly possessed of the Castle. The States vnderstanding of his designes, strengthned it againe with new troopes. <hi>Neuburg</hi> seeing
<pb facs="tcp:177491:6"/>his hopes now frustrate, and no likelihood of gaining an absolute possession of the same, growes disconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, changeth his Religion, marieth the Bishop of <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens</hi> sister, daughter to the Duke of <hi>Baueir,</hi> whose banner hee borroweth, and with whose purse hee leuies great troopes, beginnes to take the field, and in this discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent fortifies <hi>Duisseldorpe,</hi> but yet vnder a colour of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding for his owne person.</p>
               <p>The States not sleeping, sent out Prince <hi>Henry</hi> with a strong conuoy of horse, to bring moe companies into <hi>Gulick,</hi> which with those that were in before, amounted to about 2500. men. <hi>Neuburg</hi> seeing this, adheres to the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> who vndertakes the cause, makes <hi>Spinola</hi> his Generall, who hauing gathered a mightie Armie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, the best of his old souldiers from all his Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons in those parts, besides many companies newly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in, makes his <hi>rendez-vous</hi> at <hi>Maestricht,</hi> vnder a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of executing the Emperors <hi>Banne</hi> against <hi>Acon</hi> and <hi>Mullem:</hi> whereupon he makes a great Bridge at <hi>Mae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stricht,</hi> and another at <hi>Rhine-berck;</hi> but these were as well to amuse the world, and to giue an occasion of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straction in opinion which way hee would turne head, as for necessarie vse. Yet by meanes of that at <hi>Rhine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berck</hi> he had the Riuer at command. After hee had taken in <hi>Acon,</hi> hee came within Cannon shot, or not much further, before <hi>Gulick,</hi> where hee lay two or three daies, onely for a colour, and to giue no mistrust to those, whom hee intended to visit ere they expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted him. In the meane time hauing secured the <hi>Rhine</hi> aboue, for his designes, hee sends his prouision and baggage downe the same, which, then leauing <hi>Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177491:7"/>with all speede possible he meets at <hi>Wesel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The States all this while tooke no hot <hi>Alarme,</hi> but only made provision for the Armie, and al things neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie thereto belonging, to be in a readinesse at an hours warning. Yet hereupon arose sundrie opinions and doubts, of most places of the Netherlands: those of the frontiers of <hi>Gelderland,</hi> the <hi>Betow,</hi> and other places, desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Armie with all speede: others were of opinion they were in no danger at all; and the most were indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent. But the wisedome of his Excellencie (who best could finde the old Foxe by his track, and better dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne this clowd then any other) knew a storme would light ere long somewhere; wherefore, not attending the resolutions of all, and opposing himselfe strongly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the perswasions of some; hee marched presently forward, neither could any certainty be agreed of, vntil hee was come as farre as <hi>Arnhem</hi> in <hi>Gelderland,</hi> where was brought the first newes vnto him that <hi>Wesel</hi> was taken, not without suspition of treacherie within: for they might very well haue held out, till his Excellence had relieued them, which would haue beene within two dayes, or three at the most.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Arnhem,</hi> his Excellence marched toward <hi>Schenck Sconce,</hi> a Fort of great strength and import, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the mouth of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> as it diuides it selfe, one part towards <hi>Arnhem,</hi> retayning his name; the other towards <hi>Nieumegen</hi> and <hi>Bommel,</hi> losing it, being called <hi>Vahalis,</hi> or the <hi>Wael,</hi> where the whole Armie vnited it selfe into one body, to the number of betwixt eleuen and twelue thousand foote, which made one hundred and foure and thirtie Companies, and three thousand
<pb facs="tcp:177491:7"/>horse, two thousand and fiue hundred whole armed, fiue hundred Bedets, fit and readie for seruice, if neede required, but not whole armed. So exquisite and braue an Armie, for the choice of able bodied men, and reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute spirits, so well clothed and armed, and generally so well exercised in the vse of their Armes, to the great commendation and honour of their Chiefes and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, that these many yeares the like hath not been shene in these Countries, wanting nothing but an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, to giue testimonie of their valour, yea though hee were double their number.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Rendez vous</hi> being at <hi>Skenck Sconce,</hi> vpon the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth of <hi>September,</hi> 1614. The Armie marched from hence to
<note n="*" place="margin">Or Elten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh.</note>
                  <hi>Elten</hi> on the Hill in <hi>Cleueland,</hi> they being diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into three maine bodies, which made the Vantgard, the Battaile, and the Rereward.</p>
               <p>The first body was lead by the Illustrious Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> himselfe, containing sixe Companies of his own Guardes: nine and twentie Companies of Sir <hi>Horace Vere,</hi> Lord Gouernour of the <hi>Brill</hi> his Regiments: Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Companies of Colonel <hi>Ogles</hi> Regiment, and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene Companies of <hi>Wallons,</hi> of Count <hi>Iohns</hi> Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>The second body was lead by Count <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Nas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sau,</hi> and contayned sixteene Companies of <hi>French,</hi> of Monsieur <hi>Chastillions</hi> Regiment: sixteene Companies of <hi>Courtemers,</hi> and eleuen Companies of <hi>Frizons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third body lead by Count <hi>Ernestus,</hi> Marshall of the Armie, contayned ten Companies of <hi>Scots,</hi> of the Regiment of Colonell <hi>Broge:</hi> ten Companies more of <hi>Scots,</hi> of the Regiment of Colonell <hi>Henderson.</hi> twelue
<pb facs="tcp:177491:8"/>Companies of Sir <hi>Edward Cecils</hi> Regiment, who was Generall for his Maiestie at <hi>Iuliers,</hi> and nine Companies of <hi>Almaines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This goodly and braue Armie, being come to <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tham,</hi> a little Towne, standing vpon a great and high Hill, about two Duch miles from <hi>Schenke Sconce</hi> (where may bee seene the goodliest prospect one of them, I thinke in the World, for varietie of Landschap) it mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to <hi>Emerick</hi> (or <hi>Embrick</hi>) whither being come by one or two of the clock in the afternoone, they lay all night before the Towne: on the next day, being the eighth of <hi>September,</hi> the Towne yeelded to his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, who put a good Garrison into the same, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of Count <hi>Hohenloo,</hi> and the yong Lord of <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derod.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The afternoone this day, the Armie remoued to the Northwest of the Towne, where it continued that night, and all the next day, building in formall order, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting a longer stay there.</p>
               <p>Vpon the tenth of <hi>September,</hi> Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> marched away betime in the morning, his diuision hauing the Vantguard, Count <hi>Ernest</hi> the Battaile, and Graue <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> the Rere, thinking without doubt to haue encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the <hi>Marques Spinola,</hi> neare vnto the Towne of <hi>Rais,</hi> whom wee vnderstood was comming by that way, to ferce the Towne, because hee was defeated of his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose the day before, attempting to surprize it on the suddaine, with certaine of his troups sent from <hi>Wesel</hi> in sloopes or long boats, downe the Riuer of <hi>Rhine,</hi> who were by those of the Towne well beaten back, with some few slaine. But not being so happie as to meete
<pb facs="tcp:177491:8"/>with him, wee quartered on the North North-East side of the Towne, where the Armie remayned till the breaking vp thereof.</p>
               <p>Vpon the eleuenth of <hi>September,</hi> the Companies were drawne forth before the Towne of <hi>Reis,</hi> which for a smal time stood out, insomuch as certaine Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon-men (or Voer-men, as they call them) being with some Souldiers in an Hop garden, by the walls of the Towne, were shot; whereupon his Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie himselfe on horse-back, went to the Gates, and told them vpon the Walls, that if they discharged e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen but one shot more, he would beate the Towne about their eares, and giue the spoile to the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers: hereupon (though with much difficultie and doubt) they yeelded.</p>
               <p>Vpon the twelfth day, his Excellence drew out of the Armie, about 400. foot, who with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of <hi>Lambert Charels,</hi> Gouernour of <hi>Nieumegen,</hi> tooke in these Townes ensuing, <hi>viz. Colker, Raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stein, Kennop,</hi> and <hi>Gough,</hi> and returned the same night vnto the Armie.</p>
               <p>Vpon the thirteenth of <hi>September,</hi> his Excellence sent out seuen hundred to take in <hi>Greete.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Vpon the fourteenth and fifteenth of <hi>September,</hi> his Excellence (at the request of the Princes <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> and <hi>Newburg</hi>) considering the pitifull estate of the Countrie, spoiled and harried by either Armie, to haue them dissolued, sent Mounsieur <hi>Marquette,</hi> Lieftenant Generall of the Horse, and the Captaine of his Guard, to treat with <hi>Spinola</hi> about it, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusing the same without the giuing ouer of <hi>Gulick,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177491:9"/>which his Excellence vnderstood not to appertayne to this yeares action, by reason the States haue held it these foure yeares for some priuate and important consideration, sent for more Companies, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued the treatie. Whereas <hi>Spinola</hi> had made fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions at both ends of his bridge, &amp; was in hand with a skonce without the Towne of <hi>Wesel,</hi> ground was laid forth to doe the like at the end of our bridge, on the other side of the <hi>Rhine</hi> against <hi>Rais,</hi> but not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solued vpon.</p>
               <p>The eighteenth and nineteenth of <hi>September,</hi> his Excellence with all the quarter Masters, went vp the Riuer of <hi>Rhine,</hi> on the farther side, to view ground for new quarters, which was appointed, but after ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected, by reason it was said <hi>Spinola</hi> purposed to march and winter his men in <hi>Mark-land,</hi> whom, if he did, his Excellence purposed to follow.</p>
               <p>On the twentieth, one and twentieth, and two and twentieth day: All lay still, and nothing attempted. Vpon the three and twentieth day, his Excellence drew forth his whole Armie of foot, and put them into <hi>Battaglia,</hi> which was a goodly sight, to see a large and spacious field, late laden with Eares, now with Armes, the aire depainted with so many sundry co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, so many Pikes advanced, that they seemed a mightie and mouing wood, the order and resolution of so many gallant Souldiers, that now I beleeued that saying, and found it true, That <hi>a braue Armie is the best of the three fairest sights in the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was ordered and disposed in this manner. The Vantguard (as also the Battaile and Rere) consisted
<pb facs="tcp:177491:9"/>of a Vantguard, Battaile, and Rere, Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> his Guardes, and ten Companies of Sir <hi>Horace Veres,</hi> making the Vantguard of the Vantguard, in two bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, each distant from the other an hundred foot, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther body being againe diuided into foure diuisions, or quarters, fiftie foot each from either: the Battaile consisted againe of two bodies, one contayning ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Companies of Colonel <hi>Ogles,</hi> being likewise diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into foure diuisions, fiftie foot asunder, the other nine Companies more of Colonel <hi>Veres,</hi> being three hundred foot backward, and distant one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 400. foot, a space to receiue the Vantguard if occasion required: the Rere six hundred foot behind the Battaile, and opposite to the Vantguard, consisted of twelue Companies of <hi>Wallons</hi> in one body, diuided as the other into foure diuisions, fiftie foot distant, so that the Vantguard (as the Battaile and Rere) stood in forme of a Crosse, according as I haue described it.</p>
               <p>The Battaile, obseruing the same forme in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects, had in the Vantguard ten Companies of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Broges,</hi> and ten of <hi>Hendersons.</hi> The Battaile of the Battaile consisted of twelue Companies of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Cecils,</hi> and foure Companies of <hi>Almaines,</hi> (distant from the battaile of the Vantgard two hundred foot standing euen against it) in the Rere of the Battaile were the rest of the <hi>Almaine</hi> companies. The Vant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard of the Rere, consisted of sixteen companies of <hi>Courtemer,</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Colonel: the battaile, of sixteene companies of <hi>Chastilions:</hi> The Rere of the Rere, of eleuen <hi>Frizon</hi> companies.</p>
               <p>The Vantguard was 4292. strong, the Battaile
<pb facs="tcp:177491:10"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177491:10"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177491:11"/>3824. the Rere 4066. and the entire breadth of this Order, as they stood readie to fight, 2800. foot.</p>
               <p>The foure and twentieth of <hi>September,</hi> a prayer was said throughout the Armie, for the preseruation and successe thereof, as also throughout all the vnited Prouinces of the States.</p>
               <p>The fiue and twentieth day, Nothing obserued.</p>
               <p>The sixe and twentieth, the Horse contayning eight and thirtie troups, with those of <hi>Brandenburgs,</hi> were showne in the field in order of fight: their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was in forme of a Pile or wedge, called of the old <hi>Romans, Cuneus,</hi> narrow in the front, and dispreading themselues broad in the wings. In the front were the troups of Prince <hi>Henrie</hi> of <hi>Nassau,</hi> and <hi>Rijhouen:</hi> next to those the troups of <hi>Megang, Wagenman,</hi> and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellus Bax:</hi> the distance of ground from the right wing of <hi>Megang,</hi> to the left of <hi>Bax,</hi> was 1370. foot. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind those, the troups of <hi>Stalkenburg</hi> and <hi>Marquette,</hi> possessing the distance of 2040. foote. Then the troups of <hi>Vanderwel,</hi> and <hi>Smelsange,</hi> hauing the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of 2520. foot. Last of all <hi>Villebon,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Bax,</hi> in distance 3000. foote, which was the entire breadth of this Order.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>September</hi> the seuen and twentieth, his Excellence at night sent foure and twentie troups of his owne, and sixe of the Marques of <hi>Brandenburgs,</hi> with foure or fiue hundred foot in waggons, commanded by Count <hi>Henrie,</hi> into <hi>Merck-land,</hi> whither two com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of <hi>Dragounes,</hi> and one of <hi>Carbines,</hi> were sent before, with which forces they tooke in the townes hereafter named.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177491:11"/>
               <p> His Excellence sent <hi>Rocolier,</hi> a Serieant Maior of the <hi>French,</hi> vnto <hi>Gulick,</hi> with orders to draw the Companies from thence, and to take in the Townes thereabouts, hereafter named.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>September</hi> the eight and twentieth, Prince <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice,</hi> in case <hi>Spinola</hi> should stop or hinder any of these forces, sent command that all men should keepe their quarters, and be ready vpon any sudden war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to march after them if need required.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>September</hi> the 29. and 30. order was giuen that no Souldier or Officer should depart the Armie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Excellences passe, and that no souldier or waggon should goe out for forrage without conuoy.</p>
               <p>Vpon the first of <hi>October,</hi> about seuen a clocke in the euening, ten Companies of Colonell <hi>Broges</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, and three of the <hi>Suisses</hi> or <hi>Amaines,</hi> had their quarters burned by mischance. How or where the fire began, it is vncertaine. They say, by the carelesnesse of a <hi>Suisses</hi> wife, who throwing a candle and candlesticke at her husbands head, being both drunke, let it alone in the straw till it had fired the quarter, which we beheld from the beginning to the end, being at supper neere the place.</p>
               <p>About this time, or shortly after, the Boores of the Countrey acquainted his Excellencie with the danger the whole Armie was in of drowning, if the enemie should cut the banke of the Riuer by <hi>Bislick,</hi> which three or foure might easily haue done in two houres: wherefore he appointed certaine troopes to watch thereabouts euery night. The water so much now began to increase, that Sir <hi>Horace Veres</hi> quarter
<pb facs="tcp:177491:12"/>remoued to the other side of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> by the bridge of boats laid ouer against <hi>Rais,</hi> by which I tooke the breadth of the <hi>Rhine</hi> there, which was six hundred of my paces.</p>
               <p>On the second day of <hi>October,</hi> at the instance of <hi>Neuburgs</hi> Ambassador, who was come to his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence before to accept the conditions first offered, it was on both sides agreed, that after twelue a clocke the same day, there should be no more taking in of Townes on neither side, till the intercedent Princes had compounded their differences; and lay still.</p>
               <p>On the third and fourth daies of <hi>October,</hi> the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassador of <hi>England,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Wooton,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> Ambassador, <hi>La Refuge,</hi> came to the Armie, whom Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> met with foure troopes of horse, as I take it, (for they went so close, I could not well dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne them) some three quarters of a mile from the Armie, conducting them into <hi>Rais,</hi> where they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained.</p>
               <p>Vpon the ninth day they were inuited to <hi>Spinola's</hi> Leaguer, and that night went to <hi>Wesel.</hi> The <hi>English</hi> Ambassador was receiued at the entrance into the quarter by <hi>Neuburg,</hi> and the Marquesse <hi>Spinola,</hi> who, attended on by many Gallants, <hi>Italians</hi> and <hi>Spaniards,</hi> on horsebacke, met him there, and alight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off from their horses, and the Ambassador com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out of his Coach, saluted one the other: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter some few complements, they mounted him on horsebacke, and lead him betweene them thorow their quarters into Marquesse <hi>Spinola</hi> his Tent, with the principall of their followers, where they remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:177491:12"/>till dinner was brought in, what time <hi>Neuburg</hi> and <hi>Spinola</hi> brought him in to dinner. The first quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was Sir <hi>Griffin Markhams,</hi> a little within which was raised a plat, whereon were planted three pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Ordinance, which were discharged as they passed by. The foot stood also in troops, fiue deepe, the pikes on the one side, and the shot on the other, in their
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>That is,</hi> 24. <hi>foot distant, to auoid the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non where it plaies among troopes close together.</hi>
                  </note> open open order, discharging by volleies as they passed. The horse being Carbins and Lanciers about twentie troopes, veiled the Cornets, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged their Pistols as they passed. The whole number of horse and foot thus standing, was ghessed to be about seuen thousand. But ere I passe further, know the summe and strength of the enimies Armie as well as our owne.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>The Marquesse <hi>Spinola's</hi> Armie.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ambrosius Spinola,</hi> Marquesse of <hi>Venafri,</hi> an <hi>Italian,</hi> Generall.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Don Lewes de Velasco,</hi> a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> Generall of the Horse.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bartholomaeo Zanchez,</hi> Lieutenant Generall of the Horse.</item>
                  <item>The Count of <hi>Bucquoy,</hi> Generall of the Artillerie, but not present in person.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Monsieur Wingard,</hi> Lieutenant Generall of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillerie.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Baltasar Lopez,</hi> Serieant Maior Generall.</item>
               </list>
               <pb facs="tcp:177491:13"/>
               <list>
                  <head>Colonels of <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Don Iuego de Boraga,</hi> Gouernor of the Castle of <hi>And<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warpe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Simon Antonius.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Don Iuan de Menesis.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Each hath twelue Companies in his Regiment, euery Regiment containing a thousand men, so that the Regiments of <hi>Spaniards</hi> are three thousand.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Italians.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Marcello Giudice</hi> hath only twelue Companies, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting of 1900.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Wallouns,</hi> or those of <hi>Artois</hi> and <hi>Hennegou.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Count of <hi>Holstrate,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Monsieur de Mottry,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Monsieur Gulsene.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Each hath fifteene Companies in his Regiment, euery Regiment containing 3000. men, in all 9000.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Burgonians.</head>
                  <item>The Baron of <hi>Balanson,</hi> Colonell of eight Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, in all 1000.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Almaines.</head>
                  <item>The Count of <hi>Embden,</hi> Colonell often Companies, in all 3000.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Irish.</head>
                  <item>The Baron of <hi>Dungannon, Tyrones</hi> sonne, Colonell of eight Companies, wherein are a thousand <hi>Irish.</hi> So that the summe of <hi>Spinola's</hi> Armie is 18900.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The <hi>English</hi> Ambassadour hauing remained a small time at <hi>Wesel,</hi> returned backe, and came to <hi>Santen,</hi> the appointed place for the treatie, where
<pb facs="tcp:177491:13"/>he with the other Ambassadors lay vntill about the latter end of <hi>Nouember,</hi> all which time was spent in sundrie ouertures on either side, and drawing these ensuing Articles as indifferent as possibly they could deuise for either partie, whereby an absolute and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall peace might be concluded, as well to auoid the shedding of Christian bloud, as the miserable vasta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Countrey, which was in so short a time so harried and spoiled, that the poore Inhabitants had little left them saue their bare houses. To which Articles the Duke of <hi>Neuburge</hi> set to his hand, but <hi>Spinola</hi> making many excuses and delaies, draue off the time from day to day, which our Ambassadour perceiuing, would brooke no longer, but hastened and determined forthwith to depart. <hi>Spinola</hi> percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing it, sent Count <hi>Octauio,</hi> an <hi>Italian,</hi> Post in the night (the gates of <hi>Wesel</hi> for that purpose being left open for him) to <hi>Santen,</hi> to intreat him to stay but till the next night, in which time hee assured him a messenger would come from <hi>Bruxels,</hi> by whom hee should know the Archdukes minde. Our Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor (to vse his owne word) being wonne by <hi>Spino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laes</hi> ciuilitie, staied till that night, in which time there came indeed a Courrier or Post from <hi>Bruxels,</hi> with Letters from the Archduke, (notwithstanding <hi>Pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kius</hi> was in the treatie at <hi>Santen</hi> as his agent) by which Letters the Archduke seemed to like and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low very well of the Articles, intimating withall his consent thereunto, in generall termes, as, saying hee would accord and signe, but did not. <hi>Spinola</hi> made shew likewise to allow of them. But touching that
<pb facs="tcp:177491:14"/>Article &amp; point, of quitting the engarnisond towns, as <hi>Wesel,</hi> and the rest, his answere was, hee knew not the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> his master his pleasure, and for his owne authoritie, it was not sufficient and strong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. Hereupon the Ambassadors seeing all their labour in vaine, and <hi>Spinola</hi> intending nothing else then to gaine time by playing fast and loose in this manner, returned, nothing to any purpose (as you see) in many weekes effected.</p>
               <p>A day or two after Sir <hi>Henry Wooton,</hi> our Ambas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sador, returned, which was about the first of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> or latter end of <hi>Nouember,</hi> the Armie of Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> brake vp, euery Companie returning to his Garrison, hauing laien in the field very neere foure moneths, <hi>viz.</hi> from the eleuenth of <hi>September</hi> vnto the second of <hi>December,</hi> hauing endured much by reason of the vnseasonablenesse of the weather and dirtinesse of the place, being subiect to euery inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and ouerflowing of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> insomuch that on the very day of their departure, the souldiers mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to the ships almost vp to the knees, and the waggonmen were glad to let their waggons swimme to saue their horses.</p>
               <p>This is the summe of this last yeares businesse in <hi>Cleueland,</hi> which hath so filled the world with ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and those Countries with feare. What this yeare will produce, euent must shew. He that is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and the policie of <hi>Spino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> (being the most able Generall he hath had in the Low Countries these many yeares) will not imagine that he will giue <hi>Wesel</hi> ouer in haste, hauing fortified
<pb facs="tcp:177491:14"/>it in that manner he hath done, and daily doth by all meanes possible. I rather beleeue (and truly) with Prince <hi>Maurice,</hi> that he purposeth to make it (to vse his owne phrase) <hi>Sedem Belli,</hi> the home of his Armie, and seat of his intended warre against the low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, hauing gotten footing on this side the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and a faire way into <hi>Freezland,</hi> which hee hath long aimed at, beside some aduantage vpon the Frontier parts of <hi>Gelderland, Schenk-sconce,</hi> and the <hi>Betow.</hi> As for <hi>Rees</hi> and <hi>Embrick,</hi> they are esteemed by him as balles plaied withall for a time, and recouered not with much difficultie, if occasion required. Where beside, the Iesuites and Iesuited Burgers, very likely, may proue his friends, as appeared lately by their sundrie and open affronts done vnto <hi>Vtenhouen</hi> the Gouernour about exercise of the Protestant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, setting vp <hi>Edicts</hi> and <hi>Plaecaets</hi> vpon the Gates, with threatning of banishment and confiscation of goods to whosoeuer of the towne of <hi>Embrick</hi> should come to Protestants praier or Sermon.</p>
               <p>But, <hi>Quicquidid est, timeo</hi> DANAOS <hi>&amp; dona ferentes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:177491:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The names of such Townes as Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quesse</hi> SPINOLA hath taken in this last Summer in CLEVELAND and other places.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aken.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Duren.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sounkfol.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dalen.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Barken.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Castrum.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Grauensberch.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hensberch.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sitterts.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Drusbech.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Orson.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dinxlaken.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Wesel,</hi> before our Armie came vp.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Santen,</hi> since our Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dez-vous at <hi>Schenk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sconce.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Braggon.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The townes Prince</hi> MAVRICE hath taken in.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Embrick.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rees.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Colker.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gough.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rauenstein.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Kennop.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Greete.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Linick.</hi> Which <hi>Spinola</hi> had by those of <hi>Gulick.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hamuach.</hi> Which <hi>Spinola</hi> had by those of <hi>Gulick.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Older houen.</hi> Which <hi>Spinola</hi> had by those of <hi>Gulick.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Titts.</hi> Which <hi>Spinola</hi> had by those of <hi>Gulick.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Randlerood.</hi> Which <hi>Spinola</hi> had by those of <hi>Gulick.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177491:15"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Andermach.</hi> Taken in by Graue <hi>Hendrick.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ham.</hi> Taken in by Graue <hi>Hendrick.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Soust.</hi> Taken in by Graue <hi>Hendrick.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lunen.</hi> Taken in by Graue <hi>Hendrick.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Onne.</hi> Taken in by Graue <hi>Hendrick.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lipstots.</hi> Taken in by Graue <hi>Hendrick.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hurst.</hi> Taken in by Graue <hi>Hendrick.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cleue</hi> was possessed by <hi>Brandenburg</hi> before our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie came vp.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The names of our English <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and Commanders at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent</hi> in the Low Countries.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>Sir HORATIVS VERE Lord Gouernour of the BRILL.</head>
                  <item>Lieu. Colonel <hi>Metkerck.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Edward Vere.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Thomas Gates.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Henrie Carew.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Thomas Dale.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Henrie Payton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>George Hollis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Thomas Dutton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Iohn Vere.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Robert Carew.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Thomas Mewtas.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>William Louelake.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Edward Harwood.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Cooke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Woodhouse.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Bingham.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Lindley.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Burrough.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Ashley.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Myles.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Mason.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Dexter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Conway.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Rookwood.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177491:16"/>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Wynne.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Holcroft.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Euerard.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Pigot.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Connock.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Zouch.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Sellinger.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lieutenant</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Colonell <hi>Cecil</hi> his Regiment.</head>
                  <item>Lieutenant Colon. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genham.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Serieant Maior <hi>Proud.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Barnard Dewhurst.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Gerard Harbert.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Wigmore.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Zouch.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Spry.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Courtney.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Slingsby.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Clarke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Blundel.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Corbet.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Butler.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Colonell <hi>Ogle</hi> his Regiment.</head>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Charles Morgan</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Colonell.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Thomas Panton</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieant Maior.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Christopher Cleue.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Iohn Burlary.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Frier.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Shelton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Orell.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>F. Woodhouse.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Ramme.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Huntley.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Roger Orme.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Spenser.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Whom for honours sake I haue here set downe, being all either renowned for valour, or loue of Arts, &amp; to whom (for the most part) I am much beholden.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:177491:16"/>
            <head>The Articles agreed vpon at SANTEN.</head>
            <p>ARticles agreed vpon amongst the Ambassadors of the Kings, Princes, and Potentates vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written, vpon the controversies hapned betwixt the most Illustrious, High, and Mightie Princes, <hi>George William,</hi> Marques of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> Duke of <hi>Prus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sia, &amp;c.</hi> on the one side; And <hi>Wolfgang William,</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie <hi>Palatine,</hi> Duke of <hi>Newburgh, &amp;c.</hi> on the other side: Concerning the gouernement and provisionall Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministration of the Countries of <hi>Gulick, Cleue,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, being of the succession of the late Duke of <hi>Cleue.</hi> Which Articles haue beene set downe by writing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many seuerall conferences held by the said Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadors, both amongst themselues; and with those that haue beene thereto committed by the said Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> and <hi>Newburgh,</hi> and vpon the consent of the said Princes, to the most part and chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest of the said Articles.</p>
            <p>And to the end to cut off many light difficulties, which might lengthen the Treatise begun for a finall agreement, and consequently continue the oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the people of the said Countries, hinder the reestablishment of the said Princes in the common Administration of the same, and through the stay of
<pb facs="tcp:177491:17"/>the Armies and Garrisons bred diuers suspitions and inconveniences, to the great preiudice of the cōmon peace. It hath beene thought good that the said Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles should be presented by the aforesaid Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors to the said Princes, and that they should bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated to conforme themselues thereto, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of them for their owne good and quiet, and that of the said Countries, and of all Christendome, vpon promise of the said Ambassadours, in the name of their Kings, Princes, and Superiours, to maintayne the said Princes of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> and <hi>Newburgh,</hi> in the said provisionall Administration, according to the said Articles.</p>
            <div type="articles">
               <head>The Articles are these.</head>
               <p>ALL the Garrisons which haue beene put into the Townes, Castles, and other places of the Dukedomes of <hi>Gulick, Cleue,</hi> and <hi>Bergh,</hi> Earledomes of <hi>Marke,</hi> and <hi>Rauensbergh,</hi> and Lordship of <hi>Rauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stein,</hi> taken by whomsoeuer, and vnder what pretext soeuer, euen those which haue beene put into the Towne and Castle of <hi>Gulick,</hi> and into the Towne of <hi>Weesel,</hi> shall be presently drawne out: and all the Munitions that shall bee found in the same, shall bee carried away by those that brought them in. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, all the troups of both Armies shall retire them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues into their owne Countries, without any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention whatsoeuer in this behalfe, and without do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any damage to the people of the Townes, and Subiects of the said Duchies and Countries.</p>
               <p>The said Princes shall promise, to put neuer a
<pb facs="tcp:177491:17"/>place of the said Countries into the hands of a third, whatsoeuer hee might bee, but to helpe one another against all such, as by force or otherwise should pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend any thing vpon the said Countries. Yet it shall be lawful for the said Pretendors to make their claim by friendly meanes, and course of Law. No Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons likewise shall bee put or established into any Towne or Castle of the said Countries, by any man whatsoeuer; vnlesse it were by the common consent of both Princes: Who also for their gards and securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of their persons shall keepe at the most but fiftie horse, and a hundred foot a peece.</p>
               <p>The fortifications made on both sides, in the said occupied places, since the moneth of <hi>May</hi> last, shall be throwne downe and demolished, without being law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for any man hereafter to repaire them, or to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie any place in the said Countries, vntill the finall decision of the maine matter.</p>
               <p>The Church-men, Officers, Gentlemen, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, of what Religion, Facultie, and Qualitie what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer, which should haue been dispossessed of their Benefices, Offices, Houses and Goods, or should haue beene driuen away, or had absented themselues through the ill correspondencie hapned betwixt the said Princes, shall bee reestablished againe into their said benefices, offices, charges, houses and goods, without any exception; and those that shal be found to haue beene heretofore lawfully preferred to the said benefices and offices, according to the contracts, agreements, and conventions, made betwixt the said Princes, shall be thereto admitted; yet it shall not be
<pb facs="tcp:177491:18"/>lawfull for any of the said common Officers to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage himselfe particularly to the seruice, more of the one then the other of the said Princes.</p>
               <p>All innovations, both in the estate of the Church, and in politique gouernement, shall by Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners appointed by both Princes ioyntly be redressed and reestablished, and all ordered henceforth accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Treatie of <hi>Dortmund</hi> and <hi>Hall,</hi> and to the Contracts and Declarations made vpon the same, with the common consent of the said Princes and States of the Land, so farre forth as the said declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions shall not bee against the promise, made to the late most <hi>Christian</hi> King, <hi>Henrie</hi> the Great, of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and most glorious memorie, by the said Princes of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> and <hi>Newburgh,</hi> which in all points shal be throughly obserued and followed, according as it is mentioned in the Treatie of the reduction of <hi>Gulick;</hi> which Commissioners shall be chosen by the said Princes of men of qualitie, and of meanes, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the Countrie, and hauing interest in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Peace and quiet, and shall bee named within a Moneth after the date of this present Treatise. And if one of the said Princes should faile to name any within the said time, the execution of this present Article shall bee done by the Commissioners named by the other. And if it should happen that the said Deputies should bee in any doubt amongst them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues vpon the execution of the said Treaties, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts, Declarations, and promise, the states of the Prouince, which the different shall concerne, shall name two men of both Religions, which together
<pb facs="tcp:177491:18"/>with the said Commissioners shall aduise and resolue that which they shall iudge most convenient accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the said Treaties, Contracts, Declarations, and promise.</p>
               <p>The said Princes shall haue their residence asunder in the said Countries, and to that end the same shall be prouisionall diuided into two parts, without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice to their Vnion, and to the Treaties of <hi>Dort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mound</hi> and <hi>Hall.</hi> In the one of the said two parts shall be the Dukedome of <hi>Cleue,</hi> the Countie of <hi>Marke, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vensteine,</hi> and the countie of <hi>Rauenbergh,</hi> with all that belongeth and appertayneth to the Chancelrie, and Exchequer of <hi>Cleue,</hi> as also the Fees, Lands, and Lordships, seated in the Dukedome of <hi>Brabant,</hi> and countie of <hi>Flanders,</hi> &amp; the said countie of <hi>Rauenbergh,</hi> shall be seuered from the Chancelrie and Exchequer of <hi>Dusseldorp,</hi> and ioyned to that of <hi>Cleue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in the other part, shall be the Dukedomes of <hi>Gulick,</hi> and <hi>Bergh,</hi> with all their appurtinances and dependances, vpon condition that the Towne and Castle of <hi>Gulick,</hi> with all the compasse thereof, shall be put out of defence, and the said compasse reduced to a simple inclosure. In like manner, and at the same time, shall the new Fortification of the Towne Castle, and Citadell, of <hi>Dusseldorp,</hi> be also broken and demolished. And for execution of the present Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, there shall bee a Captaine or Ingenior, named by each of the said Princes, to proceed to the said de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molitions in all diligence, and without any intermis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and that at the charges of the Land.</p>
               <p>Vntill the time that the Fortifications of <hi>Gulick</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177491:19"/>and <hi>Dusseldorp,</hi> shall bee throughly demolished, the said two Townes, and their Castles, and Citadels, shall bee put into the hands of the States of <hi>Gulick, Gleue, &amp;c.</hi> which they shall commit to the gard and keeping of the same men of qualitie, faithfull, and well affected to the Countrey.</p>
               <p>And to this effect, four men shall be named by the States of the Dukdome of <hi>Gulick,</hi> 2. of each religion, for to be 2. of them Captains, and the 2. other Liefte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, &amp; by each of the Dukdomes of <hi>Cleue</hi> &amp; <hi>Bergh,</hi> and the Earledome of <hi>Marke,</hi> 2. of both Religions, to be likewise the one a Captaine &amp; the other a Liefte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, each of which Captains shall haue the cōmand of 100. men, raised in the said Land, without admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any stranger amongst them. Of these 5. Captains, 3. shalbe ordained for the keeping of the town, castle, &amp; citadell of <hi>Dusseldorp,</hi> for which they shall cast lots.</p>
               <p>The said Captaines, Lieftenants, and Souldiers, shall promise and sweare, to keepe the said places well and faithfully for the Countrey, vntill the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire demolition of the same, and to receiue into the same no man whatsoeuer, that could enterprise any thing vpon them: As also to obay no cōmand what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer, that should be made vnto them, to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice of the keeping of the place, that shall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their charge, or of the demolition thereof. Which parts so diuided, the said Princes shal cast lots for, and each of them shall gouerne that which shall befall him in the name of them both, and likewise all publike writings in both the residences shall bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spatched in the name of the said Princes ioyntly, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the hands of the Presidents of each Chancelrie,
<pb facs="tcp:177491:19"/>And a common seale of the said two Princes; about which they shall agree.</p>
               <p>Each Prince shall put in each of the two residen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, two Presidents with foure Councellors, and such number of Secretaries as shall bee found conuenient by the Princes to serue as well in the Chancelrie as in the Exchequer, which Presidents shall preside by turnes weekly, and for to beginne as also for signing, the presidence shall bee continued to him that hath had it heretofore. And the law businesses and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny matters shalbe determined by plurality of voices, without being lawful for any to addresse himselfe to either of the said Princes, to interrupt the course or execution of Iustice, or the businesses that shall bee there handled. But if any contention with the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours should arise whatsoeuer, shall be resolued vpon that behalfe in the said Chancelries, shall not bee put in execution, without hauing beene before commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to each of the Princes.</p>
               <p>And if the Presidents &amp; Counsailors of one Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celrie were diuided in opinions, the businesse shall be examined againe, and put in deliberation twice at two seuerall daies, and if they were againe diuided, the Prince of the Residence with the Presidence, shall come betwixt them.</p>
               <p>The distributions of graces, offices, and benefices, in all the said Countries, shall remaine to the said Princes; who shal dispose of them by turnes moneth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, according to their former conventions, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts, after a due information taken of the qualitie, life, and conditions, of the sutors, by the Counsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors of the Chancelries, which shall bee thereto ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed:
<pb facs="tcp:177491:20"/>and examination made of the said sutors, according to the ancient order. In the meane time, the benefice that shall bee vacant, shall bee exercised by the next Churchman of the same Religion, and Dignitie, vntill it be disposed of by the Prince: And the said person shall enioy the reuenewes belonging to the said benefice, for the time that he shall exercise the same.</p>
               <p>And if it should happen that one of the said Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces should delay by the space of three monethes, to name capable men for the parsonages, and benefices, fallen voide at his turne, it shall bee lawfull for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prince in such a case to bestow the same to men of requisite qualities.</p>
               <p>The reuenewes of the said Countries shall bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided equally betwixt the said Princes, after the payment of wages, rents, pensions, and ordinarie charges, and each of them shall receiue his share from the Receiuers thereto committed, and by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Exchecquers, without being lawfull for one of them to dispose alone, and without the other of any part of the said reuenewes, nor make any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version of the same.</p>
               <p>No contributions, or impositions, shall be raysed nor euer asked in the behalfe of the said Princes, without their common consent and allowance, and that which the States of the said Countries shal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute, eyther of their owne accord or at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of the said Princes, shall bee diuided betwixt them equally.</p>
               <p>The accompts of the Generall and particular Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers,
<pb facs="tcp:177491:20"/>both for the time since the said communion and before, shall be examined, and after information taken by the Presidents or other thereto appointed by the Exchequer of the reuenewes of the said Countries, a true estate shal be made of the same, and the Leases, Morgagements, and Debts of the said Countries shall be examined and corrected if neede bee.</p>
               <p>The places where the Writings, and Registers, that concerne the rights of both Chancelries, and Exchequers, are kept, shall bee exactly and diligently visited within a yeare from the date of this present treatie, by Commissioners therto ordained by both Princes, and a generall Inuentorie of them shall bee taken, as also a speciall one of the titles, and writings, of the Countie of <hi>Rauensbergh,</hi> which shall bee left in the Chancelrie of <hi>Dusseldorp,</hi> when the originals shall bee taken away from thence to bee brought to the Chancelrie of <hi>Cleue:</hi> And hee to whose lot the said Countrie of <hi>Cleue</hi> shall fall, shall promise to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store the said writings vnto him, to whom in the end <hi>Rauenbergh</hi> shall be adiudged.</p>
               <p>The effect of all Alienations, gifts, and morgage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments made by the said Princes before the moneth of <hi>October</hi> last shall be suspended, vntill the decision of the maine matter: but it shall bee lawfull for the Prince that shall haue alienated, giuen, or morgaged any thing out of the residence that shall befall him, to recompence as hee shall thinke good in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe of his residence, those to whom the said Alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, Gifts, or Morgagements, should haue beene
<pb facs="tcp:177491:21"/>made. And euen the Lord <hi>Kettler</hi> for the Land and Barronery of <hi>Monioy;</hi> and that prouisionally and vpon condition, that for the time to come, the sum to which the thinges alienated, giuen, or engaged, shall amount, shall bee deducted vpon his halfe, in the reuenewes of the whole of the said Estates. And as for the alienations, and engagements, that haue beene made since the beginning of the said moneth of <hi>October</hi> last, the things so alienated or morgaged shall be restored againe on both sides.</p>
               <p>The said Princes shall liue and behaue themselues in the said Countries <hi>Iure familiaritatis,</hi> according to the treaties of <hi>Dortmund,</hi> and of <hi>Hall,</hi> to the contracts and to the priuileges of the Countries, vntill the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cision of the maine matter.</p>
               <p>It is not vnderstood by this present treatie that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie reseruations, offers, contracts, or other declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that the Princes may haue giuen or done here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore in the behalfe of any of the pretendors, to the succession of the said Countries, should be reuoked, but to the contrarie the same shall remaine in the same force, and value, that they were in before the said treatie.</p>
               <p>The said Princes shall promise by the word of a Prince, and the officers of the said two Chancelries, and Exchequers, in which this present treatie shall be read, published, and registred, shall sweare to keep, obserue, and maintaine the same inviolably, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the forme and contents thereof, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uen the said Princes to giue good and due ratifications of the same within sixe weekes at the furthest. And if one
<pb facs="tcp:177491:21"/>of the said Princes should not satisfie thereto with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the said time, the same being expired he shal be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of the libertie of casting lots, &amp; to him which shall haue brought his ratification and notified the same to both the Chancelries of the said Countries, shall bee granted his choise of the residences afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said.</p>
               <p>Without expecting which ratifications, this present treatie shall bee executed in that which concerneth the departing of the Armies, and Garrisons, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molition of the fortifications before mentioned, and the reestablishment of the innouations, vpon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that at the same time that the Armies and Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risons shall retire themselues; the Towne and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle of <hi>Gulick,</hi> and the Towne, Castle, and Citadell of <hi>Dusseldorp,</hi> shall bee yeelded to the power of those, which shall haue beene appointed by the States of the Countrie for the keeping of the said places: And that for the good of publique quiet, securitie of the common administration of the said Princes, rest, and ease of the subiects of the said Countries.</p>
               <p>Done and concluded at <hi>Santen</hi> the twelfth of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uember,</hi> 1614.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177491:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Refuge,</hi> counsellor of the most Christian King in his councels of State, and Priuie; and Am bassador of his Maiestie for the pacification of the controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies of <hi>Cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, Gulick,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Du Meurier,</hi> Counsellor of his most Christian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, and his ordinary Ambassador to the States of the vnited Prouinces, deputed to the same effect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henrie Wooton</hi> Knight, Ambassador extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of his Maiestie of great <hi>Brittaine,</hi> for the pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the controuersies of <hi>Gulick,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In the name of the Elector Princes, and vnited States of the Holy Empire.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Albert</hi> Countie of <hi>Solmes,</hi> and great master of the Palatinate Electorall, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>B. Buwinchansen de Walmerode</hi> Counsellour in the counsell of the Lord Duke of <hi>Wittenbergh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the name of the States generall of the vnited Prouinces of the Low Countries.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Derick Bas Alh-Ioachim, Mark de lidama</hi> of <hi>Xicholt, Ivan Goch, W. Borr van Emerongen. Ivan Hacrsolte.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Dickenson</hi> agent of his Maiestie of great <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> to the Princes possessing.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177491:22"/>
               <p> All Ambassadours and Deputies of the Kings, Princes, and Potentates, which haue hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore assisted the said Princes of <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> &amp; <hi>Newburgh</hi> in their prouisio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall establishment in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of the succession of the late Dukes of <hi>Cleue,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:177491:23"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:177491:23"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>